[Music]
the Sam Adams awards are given out
annually to people within the
intelligence Community who've stepped
forward to blow the whistle on
corruption waste and abuse this year's
ceremony took place in Washington DC and
was awarded to former CIA agent John
kiriako who in a 2007 interview with ABC
News officially confirmed the existence
of the Bush era torture program did you
feel comfortable with the
techniques uh frankly no and I elected
to uh to forgo the training almost 10
years later and after kiriako spent 2
years in prison the Sam Adams Community
came together at American University to
add his name to the list of recipients
of the award which include the likes of
Edward Snowden and Julian Assange he
actually thought he had the audacity to
believe that this was not a rigged
system
that those who told the truth would get
rewarded that those who stood up in the
face of danger would be
praised but instead what he discovered
is he would be abandoned and sent to
prison and that those who actually broke
the law those who actually engaged in
torture prospered and went free Sunday's
event was a display of how being an
honest and dedicated in intelligence
officer can mean little when you put
your own institution at risk kiraku who
played an instrumental role in the
capturing of Abu zida in Pakistan says
that over the past couple of decades and
certainly since 9/11 the criminal
justice system in America has
effectively been politicized through
Mass surveillance he also says it has
been used more and more for
consolidating and protecting state power
than for actual security purposes the
primary mission is to protect the agency
and one of the ways that they do that or
one of the ways that they've begun doing
that since uh the September 11th attacks
in the passage uh of the Patriot Act is
to begin gathering information on
literally every American uh every
American citizen every us person that's
people who are here legally with a green
card um just so that in the event that
you become trouble for the government at
some point in the future they can go
back to what they've already collected
whether it's your emails your phone
calls your P your Facebook posts your
Twitter posts and if they need to to
begin building a case against you they
just look key name they look into the
file they find what you've been
discussing with whatever and that's how
they got you on kako what did they get
him on they got him on on disclosing the
identity of a a colleague yeah but how
did they get it huh how' they get it
though how'd they get what that
information yeah oh now I'm not 100%
sure about that but that's the way you
do it you you look at the 10 telephone
call Y kako okay so you dig out this
file you find out that he talked to one
of the uh one of the people who never
divulged by the way never was the name
but he did talk to him and innocently
thought he was in retirement and said
you know well this this guy might know
something and that's the only thing they
could really get him on and so he pled
to that they were trying to get him on
very much serious charges of course and
wanted to put him away for 30 years so
rather than take that chance with the
hanging court that exists in Alexandria
Virginia he decided he Ed to his family
to plead out on this and they they sent
him to 30 months of which he served over
23 the Sam Adams associates also double
as a support group for whistleblowers
who feel beaten and betrayed by a
government that has persecuted them
taken away their pensions sent SWAT
teams into raid their houses and made
sure that getting another job in their
respective Fields is impossible see it's
not just the fact that they have
information
they can manipulate it well they did it
with me they actually altered doc
documents that they claimed were they
were charging documents in my case they
actually altered them or they just
alleged Things based on what they think
they have you see part of this is you
don't know what they have fully you can
say they have everything but what is it
they have and what are they going use
against you and that's like the pre-
crime thing if you have the information
they'll find something to charge you
with or find something that you did
while the group of whistleblowers has
experienced firsthand and what it means
to be on the receiving end of us wrath
many are hopeful that the public will
begin to wake up Craig Murray who sat
down with the real News 5 years ago to
talk about his uncovering of the
American sponsored torture program in
usbekistan said that he sees signs of
Awakening I am much more cheerful now
than I was a few years ago because we
have seen the genuine start of a of a
meaningful popular reaction against
social control
and we've got that in uh the UK where uh
on the one hand uh you've got Jeremy
Corbin and and his uh intellectual
anti-neoliberal Insurgency if you like
uh which is taken control of one of the
major political parties uh we've got um
a similar thing happening with the S&P
and Scottish independence which is very
heavily a leftwing movement uh and in
the United States you had the Bernie
Sanders pH nominum and nobody uh would
have imagined 10 years ago that somebody
who described himself as a socialist uh
could get so close to the Democratic
nomination uh so even though you know
the United States uh presidency base may
have ended up with the two worst
imaginable candidates you can possibly
imagine in any election anywhere um uh
underneath that there's something else
happening something else bubbling up
among people so um I I'm very hopeful
now that but the human spirit is likely
to break through and we're going to see
a break in in in in this system of
Domination by a global Elite of super
wealthy